<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Notes of a researcher : Wireless Communication Research]]></title><description><![CDATA[Research and Development Systems: Wireless Communication and Engineering Systems]]></description><link>https://muratmz.github.io</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 20:02:45 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://muratmz.github.io/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Why FR-4 Is Often Inadequate for RF Design]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Many times, designers want to use FR-4 for RF and microwave circuit designs. After all, it is less expensive than other materials, like Rogers 4350, and much less expensive than reinforced PTFE composite boards such as Rogers RT/Duroid 5870. However, sometimes it is necessary to spend the money for higher quality circuit board material and processing to get good, repeatable designs.
In this paper, to demonstrate the danger of using FR-4 for some designs, I will design a bandpass filter to work in the 2.4 GHz FCC Part 15 band which is typically used for WiFi, Bluetooth, ZigBee, cordless phones, and many other applications. The filter will be designed using the microwave filter design tool that is part of the Keysight (formerly Agilent) Genesys suite of RF and microwave design software. The pass band is defined as 2.4 to 2.483 GHz. I set an insertion loss goal of 3 dB. The filter program first designs a filter which is close to the desired performance, but it must be optimized to get the performance that is closest to the desired performance. In the case of the first filter, I used FR-4 with a dielectric constant of 4.5, a loss tangent of 0.010, and a thickness of 59 mils. The metallization is 1 oz. rolled copper. Figure 1 shows the final, optimized performance.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>By Ed Troy,  Aerospace Consulting, LLC
<a href="http://www.rfcafe.com/references/articles/ed-troy/Why-FR-4-Often-Inadequate-RF-Design-Ed-Troy.htm" class="bare">http://www.rfcafe.com/references/articles/ed-troy/Why-FR-4-Often-Inadequate-RF-Design-Ed-Troy.htm</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>[PDF] <a href="http://wovre.com/docs/Why%20FR-4%20Is%20Often%20Inadequate%20for%20RF%20Design%20(by%20Ed%20TRoy)%20-%20RF%20Cafe.pdf" class="bare">http://wovre.com/docs/Why%20FR-4%20Is%20Often%20Inadequate%20for%20RF%20Design%20(by%20Ed%20TRoy)%20-%20RF%20Cafe.pdf</a></p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://muratmz.github.io/2016/11/04/Why-FR-4-Is-Often-Inadequate-for-RF-Design.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://muratmz.github.io/2016/11/04/Why-FR-4-Is-Often-Inadequate-for-RF-Design.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Ultra Wideband Antenna Design for Target Detection]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Abstract—In this paper, a four-element microstrip antenna array is
presented. The array is composed of Wilkinson power dividers which
act as feed network along with Dolph-Chebyshev distribution and fouridentical
patch antenna elements. The array elements are properly
designed to have a compact size and constant gain against frequency.
The simulated results show good agreement with the measured results
for the fabricated antenna array. Measurement shows that the array
has a peak gain of more than 12 dBi with side-lobe level of −15 dB
at 6 GHz. These characteristics make the antenna array suitable for
UWB directional uses.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://www.jpier.org/PIERC/pierc25/06.11090607.pdf" class="bare">http://www.jpier.org/PIERC/pierc25/06.11090607.pdf</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>B Kasi1, * and C. K. Chakrabarty2
1Department of Electrical and Electronics Engineering, Kuala Lumpur
Infrastructure University College, Kajang, Selangor 43000, Malaysia
2Centre for RF and Microwave Engineering, Department of Electronics
and Communication Engineering, Universiti Tenaga Nasional, Kajang,
Selangor 43000, Malaysia</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://muratmz.github.io/2016/11/04/Ultra-Wideband-Antenna-Design-for-Target-Detection.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://muratmz.github.io/2016/11/04/Ultra-Wideband-Antenna-Design-for-Target-Detection.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Japan Graduate School Directory]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="http://www.jpss.jp/en/search/" class="bare">http://www.jpss.jp/en/search/</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>via this link we can conduct MSc or PhD programs in Japan.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://muratmz.github.io/2016/11/04/Japan-Graduate-School-Directory.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://muratmz.github.io/2016/11/04/Japan-Graduate-School-Directory.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[FR4]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FR-4" class="bare">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FR-4</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>FR-4 (or FR4) is a grade designation assigned to glass-reinforced epoxy laminate sheets, tubes, rods and printed circuit boards (PCB). FR-4 is a composite material composed of woven fiberglass cloth with an epoxy resin binder that is flame resistant (self-extinguishing).</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>"FR" stands for flame retardant, and denotes that safety of flammability of FR-4 is in compliance with the standard UL94V-0. FR-4 was created from the constituent materials (epoxy resin, woven glass fabric reinforcement, brominated flame retardant, etc.) by NEMA in 1968.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>FR-4 glass epoxy is a popular and versatile high-pressure thermoset plastic laminate grade with good strength to weight ratios. With near zero water absorption, FR-4 is most commonly used as an electrical insulator possessing considerable mechanical strength. The material is known to retain its high mechanical values and electrical insulating qualities in both dry and humid conditions. These attributes, along with good fabrication characteristics, lend utility to this grade for a wide variety of electrical and mechanical applications.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>NEMA is the regulating authority for FR-4 and other insulating laminate grades. Grade designations for glass epoxy laminates are: G10, G11, FR4, FR5 and FR6. Of these, FR4 is the grade most widely in use today. G-10, the predecessor to FR-4, lacks FR-4&#8217;s self-extinguishing flammability characteristics. Hence, FR-4 has since[when?] replaced G-10 in most applications.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://muratmz.github.io/2016/11/04/F-R.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://muratmz.github.io/2016/11/04/F-R.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>